I am on a device, and I decided to look up my IP
address. This IP address is a class A address.
How do I know this? Well, IP addresses and their
subnet masks fall into one of two types: classful
or classless. Classful addresses have a pretty
organized structure for subnet masks, in that the
subnet mask number for each octet is either 0 or
255. Remember, the subnet mask dictates which part
of an IP address is the network portion and which
part is the host portion. The first three classes,
A, B, and C, all represent IP addresses in
wide use on networks. Here are the particulars.
There are two more classes you need to know
about for the exam, classes D and E. They
are not used in the same vein as classes
A through C. We don't assign IP addresses
using class D or class E addresses. Class D
addresses are used for multicast transmissions.
Class E addresses are used for research. Here are
the ranges of class D and class E IP addresses.
Going back and looking at these ranges, you may be
thinking, what about the first number of 127? An
address that uses 127 is a loopback or diagnostic
address and does not fit into this IP addressing
scheme. Let's take a look at a classless IP
address. This IP address has a subnet mask of
255.255.240.0, which means it does not fit into
the scheme of classful addresses we have covered.